Okay. All right. We're in a series on the book of Revelation. Does everybody know that? Remember
that? Some are excited. Others are, you know, like me, maybe wrestling. Anyway, the groundwork
that we have laid for the book of Revelation so far is that it is not a puzzle to be decoded,
contrary to popular interpretations. It isn't even primarily about future events,
but it is about the revealing of Jesus Christ. It is about showing us who Jesus is presently
ruling and reigning on his throne. It is written to seven real churches in the first century in Asia
Minor. It is written to encourage them. And so if John, a pastor, was writing to encourage seven
churches who were struggling with persecution, who were wanting to give up, what hope would a book be
that's about 2,000 years in the future? So there's hope here in the midst of the suffering,
for these challenging churches. And the picture of Jesus on the throne is intended to challenge.
There are churches that he's writing to that are in rebellion, that aren't listening to, aren't being
faithful, aren't doing what Jesus says. And he's giving them the same image that is going to challenge
rebellious churches, wake up stagnant churches, and encourage struggling churches. And the primary
message, again, that accomplishes that is this image of Jesus on the throne. Daryl Johnson
has these two lines that I think are really helpful for setting the context of the book. Revelation
sets the present realities in light of the unseen realities of the future. And Revelation sets the
present realities in light of the unseen realities of the present. If you could throw up that image
from our series in the book of Ephesians, essentially what Daryl is getting at here is we live, the church
lives in this in-between state between Christ's kingdom being inaugurated, which we would say happened at the
ascension, which is a thing that we don't often preach about in the American church. You always hear about
Christ's death, his blood shed on the cross. Sometimes we talk about his resurrection. We rarely talk about
his ascension. And his ascension is part of the whole gospel. If he did not, if he raised but did not
ascend, then things would look differently. Jesus raised and ascended on into heaven on the throne. And
right now this present reality, we live in a world where Jesus is ruling and reigning on a throne in
heaven, but that kingdom has not yet been consummated. It has not yet fully come to earth. And we are in
this in-between. A lot of scholars call it this already and not yet. And so what Daryl is getting at is the
book of Revelation pulls back the curtain. We've been using the curtain as an illustration to show us what
what the kingdom of heaven looks like currently in its present reality and how that impacts our reality, the more visible, tangible, physical reality. And it puts it in perspective for the future as well. Does that make sense? If it doesn't, I can't say it any better than Daryl Johnson, so we're stuck.
Let's pray again. Let's pray again. Okay. I need it. I need it. I don't know if you need it, but we all need it. Jesus, we thank you for this book that is confusing and hard to understand at times, but gives us and is intended to give us a clearer picture and image of what your kingdom looks like right now.
And oftentimes we're, we're so consumed by the tangible, visible things in front of us.
Help us to remember that we are not just physical beings, but we are spiritual beings and both the physical and the eternal come together in this book in Revelation. Give us eyes to see, ears to hear.
And God, God, I pray that this book would be a book that encourages us to live faithfully in the midst of a broken world, that it wouldn't just be intellectual exercise that we think about, pontificate about this spiritual reality, but it would become a present thing in our hearts that changes the way that we live, that encourages us to love our neighbors and to endure persecution and to whatever obedience you call us to.
God, may this book, may this image of a slain lamb on a throne truly transform who we are as a people until you return.
It's in Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
So I heard one pastor say that if you were to poll Christians in America and ask them what book you most want at your church to preach on,
that most likely many Christians would answer the book of Revelation.
But if you were to poll most pastors in churches in America, what book would they most like to preach on?
And Revelation would probably be towards the bottom of that list.
It's hard work.
It's heavy study.
And I think it's often because many congregants, and this is not anybody's fault other than maybe pop culture and one certain book series that we will not name,
has trained people to think that the book of Revelation is answering the question, when will these things happen?
And of course, like, if we're talking about tribulation and persecution and hardship, like, it would make sense for you to be in the room and say,
well, if we know this is coming, I'd like to know when and how it's coming.
Right?
It's a very pragmatic question to ask.
But I think pastors, one of the reasons there's this tension between congregants and pastors is many pastors know that that's really not the question,
and that the actual question is far less fun to answer.
Because the actual question that's being asked in the book of Revelation is, how do we remain faithful to Jesus as these things play out?
What does faithfulness look like?
In Revelation, it can become, and this is my pastoral frustration, it can become a book that Christians get obsessed with studying.
And there can be this, like, we pat ourselves on the back because we're like, man, I'm really in the word.
But the way in which we study it does nothing to transform the way that we live in our everyday lives.
And so if you've found a way to study a book of the Bible where it does not confront you as a person in your obedience to Jesus,
then you're missing the point because the whole point of the Bible is to be conforming us into the image of Jesus.
So, if you are coming to the book of Revelation and you want to ask the question, when will these things happen?
I want to put you at ease and tell you that you're in good company.
Because the 12 disciples, Jesus' closest followers, at the very end of their following him,
three years of just being with Jesus day in and day out.
Jesus finally brings up a little bit of eschatology in Matthew 24.
Eschatology just means end times, right?
He's talking a little bit about this time between when he's going to leave them and when he's going to come back.
And he tells them some things that sound hard.
And do you want to know what the question that his disciples, his closest followers, ask him?
When will these things happen, right?
It's a good question.
Like, it's the question that all of us want to know.
And John, like Jesus, pretty much ignores that question altogether.
If you read Matthew 24 and 25 this week, you'll find out that Jesus pretty much just ignores the question.
Actually, the one answer that he gives to them is, no one knows.
AKA, don't waste your time trying to predict the future.
Instead, he opts to give them a message about not being afraid, not being deceived, to stay awake, to remain faithful to the kingdom of God.
And Revelation is really serving that same purpose.
John is giving these churches, and through these churches, us, apocalyptic images to meditate on that are intended not to give us clarity on when these things will take place,
but to encourage us not to be afraid or deceived when and if they do, to remain faithful to God's kingdom even when the future is uncertain.
And another reason pastors don't really like to preach the book of Revelation is you probably wouldn't have known up to this point,
because we've been in chapters 1 through 5.
Everybody loves to preach chapters 1 through 5.
And we're going to get to chapters 21 and 22.
Every pastor loves to preach Revelation chapter 21 and 22.
You know what, the reason pastors don't want to preach the book of Revelation?
Everything I already said in chapters 6 through 20.
So it's about to get weird is all I'm saying.
The weird things, if you're like, man, this hasn't been that bad.
It's been pretty nice so far.
Yes, it has.
Chapters 1 through 5 are pretty nice.
Chapters 21 and 22, pretty nice.
The middle, it's interesting, okay?
There's lots of symbolic numbers and images.
We're going to start today a set of seven.
There's three sets of sevens coming up.
Seven seals, seven trumpets, seven bowls that go from chapter 6 to chapter 16.
And what often happens is we read them like chronological events that have to take place, asking the question, when will these things happen?
Are we in the seven seals, the seven trumpets, the seven bowls?
And again, I just want us to try and step back from that question and instead receive them as apocalyptic images to be meditated on.
It's not about chronology.
And the best illustration that I could come up with this week as I was thinking about this is how many classical music fans do we have?
Yeah.
I knew that the few in here would be eager to raise their hands because that's a very humble brag.
Yep, me, I listen to classical music.
I have, and I enjoy it, but I'm not going to say it here.
Just like I'm wearing a messy jersey today, I am a capital B bandwagon fan.
I don't really watch that much football, soccer, however you want to say it.
I'm not going to claim to be a classical music fan, but, you know, I can hang.
I can hang.
And if we think about kind of one of the more famous, well-known classical pieces in our modern time, Beethoven's Fifth Symphony, he establishes this powerful melody.
Anybody have it?
Give it to me.
See, I'm thankful somebody else did it to me, and then I still did it.
That's embarrassing.
All right.
He establishes this really clear, powerful melody, and it gets repeated, and it gets intensified.
It gets brought to climactic crescendos.
You think the song is over, and then we go back, and we loop around, and we hit a similar melody from a different angle.
We're hearing things, seeing things that sound similar but are different, that all come together into one piece.
And I introduced that as an illustration because I think that really sets up the next section, the seven seals, the seven trumpets, the seven bowls.
Because I think they are similar images aimed at kind of drawing out the same ideas, the stirring our imagination, and shaping the way that we think about this time between Christ's ascension and Christ's return.
And what John doesn't want is the same thing that Beethoven didn't want.
Beethoven did not want you to stare at the score of his masterpiece and analyze every little detail, every little note, every little rest, every little crescendo.
He didn't want you to stare at the score.
He wanted you to sit back with your eyes closed and experience the music.
And I think this is helpful for us because I think this is what John is doing with these images.
He's giving us images that are intended for us to not overanalyze and try and parse out every specific detail,
but he's trying to stir our emotions and ultimately shape our imagination about what it looks like to anchor our hope in the slain lamb who is sitting on the throne,
even when the future looks unknown.
So with the rest of our time, I'm going to hopefully give us these images in a way that we can meditate on them
and allow them to answer some questions for us that I think John did intend to answer.
Not the win question, but questions that have application for our everyday lives.
Sound good?
All right.
We have a lot of Scripture and I'm going to do my best.
So just give me grace.
Okay.
Revelation chapter six is where we're going to be.
And the first set of images that we're going to look at are famous in pop culture.
Anybody heard of the four horsemen of the apocalypse?
All right.
So that's the first set of images that we're going to look at.
It's in Revelation chapter six, verses one through eight.
And I think the question that these horsemen are going to answer for us,
if we just sit back and meditate on the images that they are,
I think they're going to answer for us the question, what kind of a world do we live in?
What kind of a world do we live in between the ascension of Jesus and the second coming of Jesus,
this time between the inaugurated and consummated kingdom?
I think the horsemen are going to give us an image of what happens in human history.
Whether it's a, some people would argue that the four horsemen are an event that happened in the past when the temple was destroyed.
Some people will argue that it's a cyclical pattern of things that happen in the present.
Some people will argue that it is a future event that has not yet happened.
My argument is that to get stuck on the specifics of whether it's a past, present, or future event
is to miss the application that John wants us to get by meditating on the images.
Does that make sense?
All right.
So eventually you can get to the point where you can spend time thinking about what specifically you think is happening there.
But my argument is that we don't have to really get there to allow it to shape our imagination and to stir our affections for Jesus.
Okay.
So Revelation 6 verses 1 through 8.
So for context, so that we remember from Quarry's message, he hears a roaring lion and he sees a lamb, a little lamb, as if slain, who's sitting on the throne.
And then John sees a scroll, which pretty much all commentators would argue is the redemptive plan of God for human history.
And that redemptive plan of God through human history is sealed with seven seals.
And there's weeping in heaven because nobody is worthy to open the scroll except for the powerful, strong lion.
No, the lamb who has been slain, he is worthy to open the scroll.
So he takes the scroll.
He now is beginning to open it.
I watched the lamb open one of the seven seals, and I heard one of the four living creatures say with a voice like thunder,
come, and I looked, and behold, a white horse, and its rider had a bow and a crown was given to him, and he came out conquering to conquer.
When he opened the second seal, I heard the second living creature say, come, and out came another horse, bright red.
Its rider was permitted to take peace from the earth so that people should slay one another, and he was given a great sword.
And we opened the third seal, I heard the living creature say, come, and I looked, and behold, and a black horse and its rider had a pair of scales in his hand,
and I heard what seemed to be a voice in the midst of the four living creatures say, a quart of wheat for a denarius, and three quarts of barley for a denarius, and do not harm the oil and the wine.
And when he opened the fourth seal, I heard the fourth living creature say, come, and I looked, and behold, a pale horse, and its rider's name was Death,
and Hades followed him, and they were given authority over a fourth of the earth to kill with a sword, and with famine, and with pestilence, and with wild beasts on the earth.
And everyone said, praise be to God.
Right?
This is the word of the Lord.
The worthy lamb, as though slain, begins to open the seven seals.
What is happening?
Exposing the events that will take place between the inaugurated and consummated kingdom of God.
And the first four seals, the four horsemen, they all look different,
but I would argue they are prophetic images describing what the world is like between the already and not yet kingdom.
It's important context for us to know that John is not inventing these symbols out of nowhere.
These are symbols that had been repeated from the prophets in the Old Testament.
John didn't just make up something.
These are John joining in the symphony of the prophetic images of the Jewish and Christian people,
and he is expounding on them and bringing them forward.
So he's not making up images.
You can read all of these horses in Ezekiel and Isaiah and other prophets.
I also want to note that each of the four seals begins with that,
and you heard me overemphasizing this.
Each of the four seals starts with a exclamation from one of the four living creatures where he says,
come.
And this can get confusing because it almost sounds like one of the four living creatures is inviting the four horsemen to come,
which seems scary, right?
Why would these people who are on Jesus's team bowing at his throne,
why are they inviting this tribulation and persecution to come?
But what I would argue, and I think is the better answer,
is that these creatures are praying for Jesus to come back.
They want Christ to come.
They're saying, Christ, come.
Christ, come.
We see in Revelation chapter one, the book says that Jesus is coming,
that he is present and actively on his way,
and all of creation is praying that Jesus would come.
But what has to happen before Jesus can come
is that the enemy of God has to be released onto the world to deceive and lead astray.
And so these creatures are representatives of creation.
Four in Jewish numerology is just a number for kind of all four corners of the earth,
the four creatures, the four living creatures.
They represent all of creation.
And I would argue that this is what we read in Romans chapter eight.
This is an image of creation crying out, groaning for Christ to return.
All of creation is broken, and all of creation groans for Christ to return.
They pray for Christ to return.
But what has to happen before that is the horsemen get to ride.
And the first horse is how I would define it as a horse.
I get, yes, you're getting a segment of Baptist preaching for the next 10 minutes, okay?
Four Ds.
The first, deception.
The first horse resembles images of Jesus in the book of Revelation.
There are actually some scholars that would argue that the first horse is Jesus
because it's so similar to some of the other images of Jesus in Revelation.
We see Jesus on a white horse with a sword coming out of his mouth.
The problem is that Jesus is going to come on a white horse with a sword in his mouth,
and he's going to be covered in blood, and that blood is his own blood.
And this horse has a bow and is coming out to conquer.
And so he's trying to have victory.
Jesus lays down his life to have victory.
He doesn't need to use the sword.
The sword is coming out of his mouth because his gospel of truth is the thing that brings salvation and judgment.
His own blood is the thing that brings salvation and judgment.
This horse is riding to conquer, and it has a bow in its hand.
And again, let's think back to our series in Ephesians when Paul says that we should put on the armor of God.
Christians put on the armor of God to distinguish the fiery what?
Arrows.
Of who?
The enemy.
Okay, so I would argue that this is deception.
This is the enemy proclaiming false Gospels to the people on earth.
It is the enemy trying to get us to put our hope in something that looks like Jesus but falls short every single time.
Jesus says, I am the way, the truth, and the life.
The enemy says, power is the way, the truth, and the life.
Wealth is the way, the truth, and the life.
Empire is the way, the truth, and the life.
Tribalism is the way, the truth, and the life.
Progressive secularism is the way, the truth, and the life.
Democratic capitalism is the way, the truth, and the life.
Insert whatever worldview or ideology you want.
The enemy will try and counterfeit the good news of Jesus with something less than Jesus.
And it is using that false gospel to try and conquer the people of the earth.
It imitates the message of Jesus.
It says, you can have peace, you can have prosperity, you can have success, but all of it is temporary and short-sighted in light of the eternal kingdom of the Jesus who comes on a white horse with a sword out of his mouth covered in his own blood.
This is the good news of Jesus.
The spiritual powers counterfeit the gospel and promise people peace through putting their hope and allegiance in something other than the lamb who sits on the throne.
So, horse number one, false Gospels, deception, the enemy trying to get, and this is unleashed at Christ's ascension.
The enemy is trying to get people to reject the good news of Jesus for a false gospel.
It's already started in the seven churches in Asia Minor.
And John wants them to see, you're being deceived.
These arrows are aimed to kill you, not to give you life.
And when people believe false Gospels, the second horse rides.
The second horse is that of division.
We saw it.
The horse is bright red.
It was permitted to take peace from the earth.
People begin to slay one another.
It's given a sword.
And here's what happens.
This is a, I would argue that this is a pattern of things that happen in society throughout human history.
When people are deceived and begin to believe a false gospel, a competing gospel, it pushes us into tribalism and a scarcity mindset.
If I believe the gospel of democratic capitalism and you believe the gospel of progressive secularism and socialism, then you and I are at odds.
We are in different tribes and we are all competing for a limited number of votes and resources and whatever.
Sound familiar?
Okay.
So we get, and it happens throughout all human history.
I'm just using an example that we can like see on the news tomorrow.
But this happens throughout all human history.
If you believe a gospel that tells you that you need to put your hope in something smaller than the slain lamb of Jesus, you will get put into a category of people.
And you and your category of people will be trying to create peace and abundance, the fruit of the true gospel, abundant life, right?
Your crew is looking for abundant life.
That crew is looking for abundant life.
And you're both believing a message that is in competition with one another.
So when we believe a false gospel, we are deceived and we are deceived and we are divided and peace gets removed from the earth.
And a side consequence is the third horse, which is that of disparity.
So we've got deception, division, disparity here, the Baptist and me.
You guys happy with that?
All right, cool.
This is so powerful.
This image that John is showing us is that the bare necessities for life and survival become as expensive as an entire day's wage.
A denarius is an oversimplified way of just saying a day's wage, barley and wheat.
These are things we have to have to survive.
John is saying when people are deceived, when they're divided into other groups and they start warring with one another,
what happens is the bare necessities to survive become hard to come by.
But notice the luxuries, the expensive things, the oil and the wine don't get touched at all.
Can we connect the dots here?
Disparity comes when we believe a false gospel, when we're divided into smaller groups of people and we start viewing each other as enemies.
Tribes form, war and conflict happen over seemingly limited resources.
It creates income and power disparities.
The rich get richer and the poor barely survive.
Can any of us think of any time in human history when this has happened?
We could be here all day giving examples, right?
I'm going to use a very common, modern example.
This could blow up bad, but you know, you guys know I'm not afraid of risk.
It's a both-sided example.
Do you guys trust me?
Okay, I don't know if I trust myself.
COVID-19 happened, right?
People who have literally lived paycheck to paycheck, barely surviving, were told that they had to be forced into their homes.
They could not work.
They could barely afford their food.
And meanwhile, what did we get images of of powerful political leaders on both sides of the aisle?
Were they at luxurious restaurants without masks, having parties with large groups of people when they told us that we weren't allowed to go to work to get our paycheck?
Okay, this happened.
And this happened, and this is one time it happened, and it has happened and will continue to happen.
This is what happens when we believe false Gospels.
Power disparity happens.
And what, I had to be careful, because here's what happens in my heart when I give that example.
I don't know if it happens to you in your heart, but what happens to me in my heart is I immediately get furious at the politicians.
And guess what the image John is giving us is intended to do?
Not make you furious at image bearers of God who have believed false Gospels.
These people in power who are benefiting from the division and disparity, who are climbing the ladder, who are all of the resources are getting hoarded at the top.
John's image is intended for us to believe and see that we do not wrestle against flesh and blood.
We do not wrestle against the politicians on the opposite party against us.
We can disagree with them.
We can voice our opinions, but they are not our enemies.
They are a people to be loved.
They are a people to be the gospel, to be proclaimed to.
We have to watch our hearts, because the enemy of God is not people.
It is spiritual forces.
And that's why Revelation is giving us a peek behind the curtain to see, look at the horsemen riding.
They are not the people.
The people have believed a false gospel.
Does that make sense?
All right, and the end result of all of this, we've got to move on, is death.
The fourth horseman is when people are divided, when they believe false Gospels, when they fight with one another and it leads to power inequality, it's just death, war and destruction and death.
And as I studied this passage, I just have kept coming back to Romans 1 this week.
The wrath of God is revealed when people suppress the truth for a lie.
This is Romans 1.
The wrath of God, and none of us like to talk about the wrath of God, but if you read Romans 1, the wrath of God is him allowing us to experience the consequences of us believing false Gospels.
And it's him continually showing up in the midst of us believing false Gospels, inviting us to repent, inviting us to see that his way is better.
The wrath of God is revealed when people suppress the truth.
They stop believing Jesus and they believe a false gospel, so God gives them over.
And this cycle just gets rolling down the hill and things get bad very quickly.
God's wrath is allowing us and the world to suffer the compounding consequences of giving our allegiance to any gospel other than the gospel of Jesus.
John's images to this point are to give people a picture of what the world looks like between the inaugurated and consummated kingdom of God.
This is heavy.
This is somewhat depressing.
Deception, division, disparity, and death.
And guess what?
We are not the only ones who are feeling the weight of this text.
Which takes us to the fifth seal.
Verse 9.
This pattern of what the world looks like in between the inaugurated and consummated kingdom gets laid out and the next seal gets broken.
When he opened the fifth seal, I saw under the altar the souls of those who had been slain for the word of God.
And for the witness they had borne, they cried out with a loud voice,
Oh, sovereign Lord, holy and true.
How long before you will judge and avenge our blood on those who dwell on the earth?
Then they were each given a white robe and told to rest a little longer until the number of their fellow servants and their brothers should be complete who were to be killed as they themselves had been killed.
The second question these images give us an answer to is how do people respond to the brokenness of this world?
If our world is full of deception, division, disparity, and death, how do people respond in the midst of that?
And the first of the seals after that pattern demonstrate how the church responds.
And that is they cry out, Lord, how long?
How long will you allow this suffering?
How long will you allow this cycle of deception that leads image bearers of God to experience the wrath of God through their own consequences and decisions?
Remember how I said each of the first four seals began with a prayer?
The representatives of all creation cried to come.
Well, guess what happens after Romans 8 when all of creation groans?
Romans 8 says that we also groan.
The church groans.
Believers groan.
We groan so much that we don't even have words.
We read it this morning.
The Holy Spirit has to pray for us because we don't even know what to pray in the midst of this broken world.
This is the images that we see in Revelation.
The creation cries out.
They groan.
Jesus, come.
The church cries out, Lord, how long are you going to allow this to happen?
And here is yet another reason why pastors do not like to preach the book of Revelation.
Because the answer is not what many of us would want to hear.
Many of us in Christianity, in Christian circles, we've been given this message that the message of Jesus is just going to make our life easier and better.
And that's not the picture we see in Revelation.
We want comfort and blessing.
We want to avoid suffering at all costs.
Oftentimes, as American Christians, we aren't even comfortable talking about other people's suffering.
We'd rather just pay no attention to that thing that's happening.
And to this day, a huge population of people are experiencing what these Christians in the fifth seal are experiencing.
They were killed for their faith in Jesus.
Not just killed as a secondary byproduct of a world that's broken.
These people were killed for not rejecting Jesus.
I got some stats to share with you from Nancy.
She's going to come up in a little bit and pray when we get to the end.
But one in seven Christians today are persecuted worldwide.
More than 388 million Christians suffer high levels of persecution and discrimination for their faith.
One in five Christians are persecuted in Africa.
Two in five in Asia.
4,849 Christians have been killed in 2026.
4,712 detained.
3,632 churches and Christian properties attacked.
The response of the martyrs is how long?
How long are you going to let this happen?
To which Jesus replies,
Do not worry.
I'm about to weaponize the church against their enemies and they will avenge your death.
No, rest a little longer.
There are more of your brothers and sisters who are going to faithfully endure persecution even to the point of death.
They're going to follow the way of Jesus and they are going to be found just like you are under.
Notice where they're at.
They're under the altar of God in heaven.
Their faithfulness, their endurance, their sacrifice is like a pleasing aroma to Jesus.
They're offering a testimony to the true gospel in the midst of all the counterfeit Gospels that are being preached.
Every other gospel is fighting and warring for their own success to climb up the ladder to get their own.
And the faithful followers of the true gospel are laying down their lives as witnesses to the world that the true gospel is the only thing that leads to life.
Now, I'm not saying we should glamorize suffering.
I'm not saying that those of us who don't experience it should long for it.
And we also shouldn't get confused that if you're being a jerk and you're getting persecuted for it, that that means you're doing the faithful thing.
I see that happen sometimes too.
You being a jerk, never mind.
All right.
I'm not saying we should long for it, but I am saying that we should be prepared for it.
And that when we see glimpses of it in the air, that our primary response should not be just to get out of it at all costs.
The church has been at its most healthy, faithful version of itself when it is persecuted.
Our persecuted brothers and sisters, Nancy, could give you testimony of how the church is growing and healthy and spreading in places where it's totally illegal to be a Christian.
I'm not saying we should look for that, want that, or hope that that happens.
But we need to realize that the way forward is not to fight back, but to keep our eyes on Jesus, who is on the throne, and prayerfully endure allegiance to the Lamb, come what may.
The sixth seal.
As the martyrs rest, the sixth seal is broken.
I am way behind time, so we're going to have to fly.
Are you good?
Cool.
The martyrs rest, the sixth seal is broken, and we see a culmination of the cycle of deception, division, disparity, and death.
When he opened the sixth seal, I look, and behold, there was a great earthquake.
The sun became black and sackcloth.
The full moon became like blood, and the stars of the sky fell to the earth as the fig trees sheds its winter fruit.
The sky vanished like a scroll being rolled up, and every mountain and island was removed from its place.
Then the kings of the earth and the great ones and the generals and the rich and the powerful and everyone, slave and free, hid themselves in caves among the rocks and from the mountains, calling to the mountains and rocks, fall on us.
This is the sixth prayer.
So far, we've had five prayers.
All creation cries, Jesus, come.
The church cries, how long?
The people who have rejected Jesus cry, fall on us.
Hide us from the face of him who is seated on the throne.
From the wrath of the lamb, for the great day of their wrath has come, and who can stand?
As the martyrs rest, the sixth seal is broken.
The culmination of this cycle happens.
The clash, the snowball is all the way down the hill, and even the most powerful, rich people can no longer stand the weight of the pressure.
Those who reject the gospel of Jesus build systems and kingdoms that are at odds with one another, ultimately collapse on themselves, and no one can escape.
And it's also interesting to me that the thing that they pray for is death.
I think as I was reading this, I heard a lot of scholars say that there's, in this text, there's almost an inherent invitation to repentance.
They look and they see that the wrath is coming from the slain lamb.
And there's this invitation that all it takes would be repentance, like we have, we've, we believed our own gospel, we repent, forgive us.
They don't want to repent, they don't want forgiveness, they'd rather die believing a lie than trust the one who was slain.
And their final prayer leads to the third question.
Who can stand?
Who can stand in the midst of this weight of false Gospels being believed, people groups being divided, deception, destruction, and death?
And as soon as that question is asked, John hears a number of 144,000 people from every tribe of the nation of Israel.
And again, we don't have time to get into the weeds in this passage.
And it has been wildly misinterpreted.
But to keep it simple, this is a common Jewish way of using numbers in a symbolic way.
It's 12,000 people from each of the 12 tribes.
And it starts with Judah, which is not how Jewish people listed the tribes.
John here is saying that Israel is the fulfillment of, that Jesus is the fulfillment of what Israel was asked to do to be a blessing to all the nations.
And he hears that all of the faithful people of Israel, the huge mass number of faithful Israelites who have walked in obedience to God, that they can stand.
They can persevere.
But more importantly, the vision goes on in chapter 7, just like in chapter 4 and 5.
Remember we heard, John heard a lion, and then what did he see?
A lamb.
In this chapter, John hears the number 144,000, 12,000 from all the 12 tribes.
And then he sees, in verse 9, after this I looked.
So I heard 144,000, 12,000 from all the tribes.
And then I looked, and behold, a great multitude that no one could number from every nation, from all the tribes and peoples and languages, standing before the throne, before the lamb, clothed in white robes, with palm trancers in their hands, and crying out with a loud voice,
salvation belongs to our God who sits on the throne, and to the lamb, and all of the creatures in heaven.
Say amen, blessing, and glory, and wisdom, and thanksgiving, and honor, and power, and might be to our God forever and ever.
Amen.
The answer to the question, who can stand?
The only people that can stand through the wrath of God are the people who have bent the knee to Jesus, both Jew and Gentile, slave and free, male and female, from every language, tribe, nation, and tongue.
If they have seen the slain lamb of Jesus as the way, and the truth, and the life, then they can stand, no matter what comes.
This is the image John wants us to meditate on, that there is a multitude of people that cannot be counted, that are persevering in the way of Jesus.
They can stand because they've been sealed by God.
We can stand if we've been sealed by Jesus.
This is Romans chapter 8.
This whole chapter 6 and chapter 7 is Romans 8.
Romans 1 and Romans 8.
But Romans 8 says, you got it on the slide there.
Yeah, there.
For I am sure that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor rulers, nor things present, nor things to come, nor powers, nor height, nor depth, nor anything else,
and all of creation will be able to separate us from the love of God in Christ Jesus.
Who can stand?
Paul is writing to the Roman church filled with Jews and Gentiles who have bowed the knee to Jesus.
These are who can stand.
We, if we have trusted in Christ, will not be separated from the love of God.
We can stand with faithful endurance through all of the hardships of life.
And then we get to the last seal.
So far we've had six seals in an interlude.
I know it's been hard to follow and I have, I'm going too fast.
All right.
The seventh seal breaks after the interlude of who can stand.
And the answer is those of us who trust Jesus.
And when the Lamb opened the seventh seal, there was silence in heaven for about half an hour.
Then I saw the seven angels who stand before God and seven trumpets were given to them.
And another angel came and stood at the altar with golden censer.
And he was given much incense to offer with the prayers of all of the saints on the golden altar before the throne.
And the smoke of the incense with the prayer of the saints rose before God from the hand of the angel.
I don't know about you, but when I was studying this, I got to the seventh seal.
I was expecting the glorious return of Jesus.
I was expecting the wedding banquet of the Lamb.
Tears being wiped away from our eyes.
And instead what we get is silence and the prayers of God's people rising up before the throne of God.
If Revelation 6 is a picture of the world that we live in before Christ's kingdom is consummated,
and Revelation 7 is a picture of the people who can remain standing under pressure,
then Revelation 8, 1 through 5, gives us instructions on how to live in the in-between.
We do not wrestle against flesh and blood.
Our response is not to fight our enemies or to avoid suffering at all costs.
Our invitation is to faithfully endure with our imagination shaped by the Lamb on the throne and to pray.
And this image of my prayers and your prayers,
the tears in your closet for the loved ones you know that are suffering,
for the consequences you are experiencing of living in a broken world,
for the cancer diagnosis,
for the unborn babies,
all of it.
Every tear you cry in your prayer closet
is lifted up before the throne of God.
And He hates it as much as you do.
He hates it more than you do.
And this is the image John wants us to meditate on
as we live in this time of suffering and deception and pain and difficulty.
The image he wants us to meditate on is our prayers
coming up before the throne of God.
And I don't know about you,
but far too often my prayers feel like they're hitting the top of the ceiling.
And sometimes that causes me to not even bring them at all.
But if we can meditate on this image of our prayers coming before the throne of God,
what would that release in our prayer life?
What would that invite us into?
This whole week I've just felt like Jesus inviting me.
It's like, I want to hear.
I want to hear what's in there.
I want you to lament the things that I lament.
I want you to hope for the things that I'm hoping for.
That your prayer is actually an active participation in my redemption plan being moved forward.
The seven seals of revelation shape our imagination
and anchor our hope in the slain lamb who is sitting on the throne,
even when the future looks chaotic or unknown.
So I'm going to ask Nancy to come up.
The visions of revelation, again, are not sheet music to be examined.
They are a symphony to be meditated on.
They're intended to shape our imagination
and encourage us to prayerfully and faithfully participate in the land's kingdom.
And I know this is heavy, and I wish that I hadn't rushed through it.
But as I was thinking about how to conclude this service,
the only thing that I could come up with was to have Nancy,
a member of our church who knows personally through her ministry at OTAN,
brothers and sisters in Christ that are currently being persecuted
for bowing their knee to the slain lamb of Christ.
Nancy's the media manager at OTAN to outreach to Asian nationals.
Their mission is to train and equip persecuted Asian pastors
to reach their people with the gospel.
So she's going to come and share a couple of images
and then lead us in prayer as we conclude.
Thanks, Ryan.
Is this on?
Can you hear me?
It's on.
Is it on?
Can you hear me?
No.
How about now?
Yay.
In 1985, a man named Otis Goodwin knew that God was calling him
to help the church in China,
but he really did not know what that looked like.
So he took this exploratory trip to China.
He had one contact,
and at night the guy led him down a dark alley
to a place he didn't know where he was going.
And no sooner had he gotten inside and met two other men
than someone knocked at the door,
and they ushered Otis down the hall into a room under a table,
said, be quiet, don't say anything.
And it turned out that the man at the door was another pastor
who stood there shaking and said,
God told me to come to this house tonight.
I don't know why I'm here.
So Otis spent time with those pastors and said,
what do you need?
I want to help you.
And in 1986, Otis and Roxanne founded Outreach to Asia Nationals,
which, as Pastor Ryan said, we minister to,
we train and equip persecuted pastors in Asia.
We work in 13 countries.
Two are outside of Asia.
And believers in these countries and across the world
live very differently than we do.
Some are disowned by their families immediately.
Some are kept from jobs or schools because of their faith.
Some are followed, harassed, and threatened.
Some have their property, including their crops, stolen.
Some have their homes destroyed.
They're detained and fined.
They're imprisoned and starved.
Some have been beaten, raped.
Some are killed in broad daylight.
And some are never seen again.
Some of the countries claim to allow religious freedom,
but it's illegal to share the gospel with someone of another faith
or someone of no faith.
Most of our pastors work six days a week
as farmers or manual labors,
but their situations vary.
I wish I could show you their faces for security.
I can't.
This is one of our pastors.
He and his wife moved into a village specifically to share the gospel.
The village did not want him there.
They're still there five years later.
This is another of our pastors.
This picture was taken in 2021.
I don't know if you can see it or not, but his feet are shackled.
He was told to close his church and stop preaching, but he didn't.
And he was put in prison.
In this particular country, family needs to bring some food to the prison
or you're not going to get enough to eat.
But the guards would eat his food.
This is his family.
That's the house where he lives.
They prayed for him while he was in prison.
He spent eight months there.
He was released.
He's recovering.
This is, so that's the pastor's family.
Yeah.
This is one of our Southeast Asia churches meeting together.
Again, I can't show you their faces.
This is also one of our churches meeting on a mountaintop.
And so is this one of our churches.
About six months ago, one of our churches who basically had nothing but chairs,
tables, and some literature were raided by authorities.
And they took the chairs, the tables, and the literature.
They told them not to meet anymore.
They'd been meeting together for over 20 years.
They started to meet online, but in their country, that's very dangerous.
So they met online for a while.
They're trying to figure out how to get back together and meet in person again.
And you can learn more about these pastors at, our website is otan.org.
Gee, I would love it if you'd visit there, click around, read the stories.
They're on the stories page.
We're also on Facebook, Instagram.
If you could share our pages with others, that's huge.
It's free for you, and it really helps us.
In America, our freedoms give us a buffet of resources for education.
If we want to study to become pastors, if we just want to know the Scriptures better ourselves.
We have colleges, universities, seminaries, online schools, seminars, certifications,
church-based training like we do here at Canvas, unlimited print materials, and of course, Bibles.
In any shade, in any color, in any language that we want.
Just before we pray for our brothers and sisters whose lives are very different from ours,
I want to share this one-minute video with you.
Now this video, I apologize, it's 15 years old, it's blurry, it's grainy, it was taken in a basement in China.
But let me assure you that even today, when some of our brothers and sisters first have a church family,
or get a Bible, the excitement looks like this.
Give me Jesus, give me Jesus, give me Jesus, give me my Lord.
Thank you.
In honor of our family members who endure daily trials for their faith, will you stand with me to pray?
Father, thank you for the freedoms we have.
Thank you for our church, for our pastors, for the countless opportunities and resources that we enjoy in freedom.
Lord, we have so much when others in our family have so little, and that is hard to understand and hard to bear.
Thank you, Lord, thank you for those you send who face extreme risk to bring the gospel to the nations,
to let our brothers and sisters know they're not alone, they're not forgotten, they're not without family.
The harvest is plentiful.
Lord, send out your workers to all nations, in all languages, among all villages, among all people groups.
Today, Lord, comfort our brothers and sisters who are afraid, who have been threatened or harmed, who have lost their leaders or their churches or their homes.
Strengthen those whose families are suffering and whose faith is wavering.
Help them to sense your presence right now and to regain hope and peace from you.
Lord, comfort the pastors and leaders who fear for their families and their congregations.
Father, when we enjoy the opportunities and resources we have, warm our hearts to remember and to lift up our brothers and sisters who have not.
Break the strongholds of evil and power that attack your people.
Hear the prayers of your children who are crying out to you.
Give these men and women and their families your mercy and your protection.
Thank you, Father.
Amen.
Don't like to rush moments like these, but if you don't pick up your children, Michelle will murder me.
So, if you're, if this has stirred some things in your heart, you want to take time to go to the prayer tent or just sit in your seat quietly,
we'll try and keep the auditorium chill zone for the next five to ten minutes.
If you got kids, please send somebody out to get them quickly because I went too long and I apologize.
So, go in peace, church.
Thank you.
Yeah.